QLOCKTWO-building instructions
Author: Christian ascho, cascho @ mac.com
Version 1.0 as of 03.10.2011
This guide includes:
The QLOCKTWO was built
by:
to:
To-do's:
CC BY-NC-SA 3.0:
Attribution
Non-commercial-
ShareAlike
Conditions 3.0
You are free: the work or the contents copy, distribute and ö do? accessible via public Variations and Or adapt the work
Contents make Under the following conditions:
Attribution - You must Name of the author / rights owner in the manner specified by him
. call
Noncommercial - This
Works or not for this content
commercial purposes.
Transmission under the same conditions -
If the licensed work or the
licensed or otherwise edit content
As recognizable as the basis for their own
Use harm? S, you may distribute the
resulting work only content
by using licensing terms
to pass on to this one
The same or similar license
are.


Foreword

These instructions deal with the construction of a so-called "word clock". The template for
This is the word clock "QLOCKTWO" by Biegert & Funk, as he? Santander watches this type
should apply.

The company Biegert & Wireless is likely to have not only a significant development effort
operated to design this clock, but also a design on the Front panel or the whole design registered.

I would therefore like to point out: This guide is intended, a word clock
QLOCKTWO in style for his own use "at home" and to build a great deal about the
so-called "physical computing", ie the connection of micro computers (microcontrollers)
and learn the real, physical world. It is not intended to (and therefore it is the
License not included) to support any commercial products or QLOCKTWOs
to build for the sale. I reject OF ANY queries within the meaning of "The original is so expensive
You can not build me one? I also pay the material ab ".

After these solemn words, a few other things:

These instructions assume that the QLOCKTWO farmer turns his head and thinks independently. It is strongly recommended that the
Manual first and then work through all begin with the Order of components. At best, you read the instructions before you order
a second time - until there are no more questions o enes arise. Many things are optional and can be exchanged: the favorable
by great white LEDs, brighter "super? ux" LEDs with a larger angle, the black film through a red, is the black frame Ribba
know in etc

And one more note on the front panel: it has been found that the easiest way to a beautiful front panel slide from one plotted
Advertising is the specialist trade. These films are not films as you can put them in the laser printer or Titenstrahldrucker, but films with
called Folienplottern be cut. This means that a device such as a CNC milling machine controlled by a knife, then the result of vector data
cuts into the drawing sheet. But only to the extent that the carrier film is not cut with. In principle, such as one would with a
Scalpel, a sticker or a dc? Carve-x film. Then you can film with the aid of a second carrier foil, the "application tape" on the
Disc stuck. These films can make the most of digital printers. If you negotiate with those that the letters themselves
triggers, it is affordable.

Well then: Preheat soldering iron and go! Or as Yoda would say:

May the Force be with you i!

Safety
Soldering iron, hot glue gun, hot glue guns and hot air
are just that: hot. Cleaning agents,
isopropanol are particularly easy
flammable.

While the construction is everywhere a bunch of tension
and electricity. In a QLOCKTWO with AC adapter
or battery operation (the recommended variants)
This is no problem. With the installation of a
internal 220-volt power supply can be fatal.
The construction of a QLOCKTWO is dangerous. Box cutters,
Scalpels, glass edges and drills are
sharp. SMD tweezers are sharp and drills. By
GOATS pinch off the legs of the components?
Drahstücke through the area. These are harmful
for the eyes.

The matrix consists of very bright "super bright"
LEDs, and a whole lot of them. Never
look directly into the LED, especially when, during
Flashing of the firmware individual LEDs
because of junk data into the shift registers
shine without multiplexing.

The matrix is ​​driven at high frequency and are
it glitches in the form of radio waves. The
Interferes with the DCF77 receiver, a problem that we
be solved. To other things that disturbed
be (pacemakers, etc.) must each be
self-care.

Soldering fumes, detergents, abrasive dust, glue,
Color, etc. are almost always harmful.

Conclusion: The construction of a QLOCKTWO is in all respects
dangerous. It is advisable to wear eye protection, gloves
and a first aid kit to hand.

And? Man or coward? Exactly. Life as a tinkerer
and in itself is dangerous, so turn on the head,
, think with sober and start working!

Version History
Left
V 1.0 10/03/2011 Created.
Latest firmware etc.: http://code.google.com/p/grosses-bastelwochenende/
The author's blog: http://christians-bastel-leben.blogspot.com/
Arduino: http://www.arduino.cc/
Jee Labs (RBBB): http://jeelabs.org/
Reichelt: http://www.reichelt.de/
Pollin: http://www.pollin.de/

List of materials
The Ribba frame is obvious (IKEA).
List of materials (continued)
A good hot glue gun.
Glue sticks for refilling.
f Pro-Tip: isopropanol, if you
the hot glue has to solve times.
(See Make: Magazine "Simple
solution for removing dried
hot glue. ")

List of materials (continued)
Photo cardboard (stationery shop)
Linial
Paper Scissors
Scalpel
Waterproof pens
Pencils

List of materials (continued)
Aluminum foil
Tapes
Tapes
f Pro-tip: A hot air gun and
Shrink tubing of different
Facilitate one size frequently? G the
Work.

List of materials (continued)
A good, fine soldering iron
A "third hand" is
a good friend
(Conrad € 5, -)
A Bestückunsrahmen is not
cheap, but it simplifies the work
immensely. But it is also without.
Soldering grease from the hardware store
Desoldering
Solder with a core of
Flux
List of materials (continued)
Sufficient silver wire
(About 11-12 meters) f Pro-Tip: Plug-in board connectors
are not absolutely necessary,
facilitate the work but
significantly (Reichelt € 3.80).
One set is sufficient.
colored strands
List of materials (continued)
? Area pliers for pulling
the silver wires SMD tweezers
With pincers? Achem terminal
To nip off the head
Component legs
f Pro-tip: stack of paper holder
can be good
Provide services when
you are alone.
List of materials (continued)
7 * 220 ohms
Resistance
3 * breadboard
1 * RBBB (Really Bare Bones Board)
f Pro-Tip: These materials (without RBBB and DCF77) are available in a ready-made shopping cart under
http://secure.reichelt.de?ACTION=20; AWKID = 30 025
The RBBB there under http://jeelabs.com/products/rbbb
It is the DCF77 receiver at http://www.pollin.de
* 1 green LED
1 * quartz watches
1 * DCF77 receiver
1 * Real time clock
RTC1307
with base
* 1 Battery
with holder
1 * Z-diode
3 * Tact
1 * 1 * LED yellow light-dependent
Resistance
114 * White LED
with great
Ö? Opening angle
4 * 74HC595
Shift-register
with bases
2 * UDN2981A
Darlington Arrays
with bases
List of materials (continued)
No. Description Unit Price Quantity Price
Mini Quartz watches 0.032768, 0.032768 MHz, TC38 1 0.15 € 0.15 €
220 1/4W Carbon Film Resistor 1/4W, 5%, 220 ohms 0,10 € 10 € 0.33
74HC IC-SCHALTU NG 0,30 € 4 595 € 1.18
A photoresistor 906 011 1 0.95 € 0.95 €
APS 300 plug-in power supply, 600 mA max, "EuP" compliant 7,35 € 1 € 7.35
CR 1225 lithium coin cell, 3V, 38 mAh, 12,5 x2, 5 mm 1 0.75 € 0.75 €
DS 1307 Real Time Clock I ² C 56B NV SRAM, DIP-8 2,35 € 1 € 2.35
GS 16 IC sockets, 16-pole, double spring contact 4 0.20 € 0.050 €
GS 18 IC sockets, 18-pole, double spring contact 2 0.12 € 0.060 €
GS 8 IC socket, 8-pole, double spring contact 0,040 € 1 € 0.040
H25PS050 Streifenrasterplati point. Laminated paper, 50x100mm 0,81 € 3 € 2.43
CTH 12-1 button cell holder for Ø 12 mm € 1.05 1 1,05 €
5-05000 WAS LED 5mm LED, ultra bright, clear, clear, white 0,24 € 114 € 27.36
SILVER 0.6 mm silver wire, diameter 0.6 mm, length: 10M 1,75 € 1 € 3.50
SLH 56 GE LED, 5mm super bright, colored, clear, yellow 0,080 € 1 € 0.080
SLH 56 GN LED, 5mm super bright, colored, clear, green 0,070 € 1 € 0.070
CONNECTOR BOARD DBS jumper jumpers set 3,80 € 1 € 3.80
Tact BUTTONS 3301D 6x6mm, Height: 12.5 mm, 12V, vert 0,16 € 3 € 0.48
UDN 2981 A Source Driver, DIP-18 € 1.75 2 3,50 €
IF 3.0 0.5 W Zener diode 3.0 V 0,040 € 1 € 0.040
22K 1/4W Carbon Film Resistor 1/4W, 5%, 22 K ohms 0,10 € 10 € 0.33
Total: € 56.06
The item numbers are those of the company Reichelt. In addition we need from Ikea, Pollin and Jee-Labs
Ribba frame 15,99 € 1 € 15.99
810 054 DCF receiver module DCF1 4,95 € 1 € 4.95
Really Bare Bones Board RBBB 13,50 € 1 € 13.50
Total: 90.50 €
This is of course still Kleinkruscht: Photo Paper, consumables such as solder, wire, etc.
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)

Preparing the protoboard
In the schematic diagrams for wiring
The boards are the breadboards "ideal"
depicted. Each series has always three holes. In reality the situation is different. In the example above, the upper
Series almost always three holes, but only the bottom two rows of holes.
Unfortunately, it's different in almost every board a bit.
Thus we subsequently easier on the board side
deal ends? that has no copper, we distinguish ourselves
Markings on the board. These are
Permanent marker and a ruler.
We draw red lines for the contact? EXT, later by the silver wire
to Vcc ("voltage of the common collector" - Plus) connected
and blue lines are those established later with the silver wire
to GND (ground, as the experts say). The intermediate
Three rows are separated by black lines.
R
eIHE
C V c
Z
wipe line R
eIHE GND

Preparing the protoboard (continued)
So you look at the wiring breadboards
not wasting, glued on one small chip templates.
You need the template from the 74HC595 shift register 4 times that of the UDN
Darlington Array 2981A 2 times of the RTC and the RTC1307 1 times. The
Positions? One round on the schematic wiring diagrams of the
Cathode-multiplexer Multiplexer anode and the control board (on the following
Pages).
Q1
Q2
Q3
Q4
Q5
Q6
Q7
GND
VCC
Q0
SER
OE
STCLK
SHCLK
MR
Q7 '
Q1
Q2
Q3
Q4
Q5
Q6
Q7
GND
VCC
Q0
SER
OE
STCLK
SHCLK
MR
Q7 '
Q1
Q2
Q3
Q4
Q5
Q6
Q7
GND
VCC
Q0
SER
OE
STCLK
SHCLK
MR
Q7 '
Q1
Q2
Q3
Q4
Q5
Q6
Q7
GND
VCC
Q0
SER
OE
STCLK
SHCLK
MR
Q7 '
X1
X2
VBAT
GND
VCC
SQW
SCL
SDA
IN1
IN2
IN3
IN4
IN5
IN6
IN7
IN8
VCC
OUT1
OUT2
OUT3
OUT4
OUT5
OUT6
OUT7
OUT8
GND
IN1
IN2
IN3
IN4
IN5
IN6
IN7
IN8
VCC
OUT1
OUT2
OUT3
OUT4
OUT5
OUT6
OUT7
OUT8
GND
4 * 74HC595 shift register
2 * UDN2981A
Darlington Array
1 * RTC1307
Real-Time Clock
Attention! The stickers
are smaller than the chip, since
yes the legs of the chip or
the version still around it
must fit.
Attention! The stickers
have the same small
"Noses" like the chips. On
the right direction
parts!
Here we go!
Ok. We are now so far that we can solder together the first board. At
the insane amounts of stripping and tinning of Cables
to spare, you can connect to on the boards very well
Jumper wires from a range of plug-in boards take.
Also provides an SMD tweezer good services to the small bridges in the
Board to fumble.
Those who have no frame assembly should be a second person (friend / speaker,
Have partners / speaker, siblings, parents, children, etc.) at hand.
The jumpers have different lengths. Each length has its own
Color.
When soldering, it necessarily
Make sure that the solder well
and clean. Cold solder joints
are subsequently difficult to
? Ends. First leg component and
Heat the board, then solder
. add
Better double-check before
and, if necessary resolder.
The circuit boards and sockets
Keep out of lot. (The chips
but know we have the
Versions.)
First Leg and copper heat
Second Solder admit
Third Five seconds does not move
The cathode-multiplexer
First, you just soldered the wires (always with the? Next
Components start).
The small connector can be good even out of silver wire
nipped off legs or bend of components.
Links: The holders for the
Au chips? Öten (with respect
the direction of the "nose").
Right: The back of
the silver wires for Vcc
and GND (ground).
Q 1
Q 2
Q 3
Q 4
Q 5
Q 6
Q 7
GND
V
C. C.
Q 0
SER OE
ST
CLK
SH
Q CLK MR
7 '
Q 1
Q 2
Q 3
Q 4
Q 5
Q 6
Q 7
GND
V
C. C.
Q 0
SER OE
ST
CLK
SH
Q CLK MR
7 '
S
he
ial-I
n
(V
om A
Noden-
M
ultiple
x
he)
O
utput
Enable
S t
or
e
-
Clock (La
t
ch)
S
he
ial-
Clock
Q0-Q7-Q0 and Q2
Matrix (GND)
Q3-Q6 one each cathode
the corner LEDs. Top left,
top right, bottom right,
bottom left.
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)
First Column
the LEDMatrix!
The resistors
are optional. They
to the LEDs
. protect
The anode multiplexer
Q 1
Q 2
Q 3
Q 4
Q 5
Q 6
Q 7
GND
V
C. C.
Q 0
SER OE
ST
CLK
SH
Q CLK MR
7 '
Q 1
Q 2
Q 3
Q 4
Q 5
Q 6
Q 7
GND
V
C. C.
Q 0
SER OE
ST
CLK
SH
Q CLK MR
7 '
S
he
ial-I
n
(V
om RBBB)
S
he
ial-
O
ut
(For K
a
methods-
M
ultiple
x
he)
O
utput
Enable
S t
or
e
-
Clock (La
t
ch)
S
he
ial-
Clock
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)
IN
1
IN
2
IN
3
IN
4
IN
5
IN
6
IN
7
IN
8
V
CC
OUT
1
OUT
2
OUT
3
OUT
4
OUT
5
OUT
6
OUT
7
OUT
8 GND
IN
1
IN
2
IN
3
IN
4
IN
5
IN
6
IN
7
IN
8
V
CC
OUT
1
OUT
2
OUT
3
OUT
4
OUT
5
OUT
6
OUT
7
OUT
8 GND
Out1-Out8-Out1 and Out2
to the anodes of the matrix
First Series
the LEDMatrix!
The anode is at the top of the same multiplexer
with the cathode-multiplexer. Then come down
to strengthen the UDN2981A chips to do so.
Links: The holders for the
Au chips? Öten (with respect
the direction of the "nose").
Right: The back of
the silver wires for Vcc
and GND (ground).
The control board
The control board is the "heart" of our
QLOCKTWO and thus slightly more expensive.
To get not confused,
you put the components in the sample times
the prototyping board and marks the
And outlines important points with a
Permanent marker.
RBBB
GND battery (covered later by a battery holder!)
Positive pole of the battery
yellow / green three-button connectors
LED terminals
S
he
ial-
O
ut (for A
Noden-M
ultiple
x
he)
Sig
signal v
om DCF77 receiver
O
utput
Enable
T
branch
he
"M
ode "
T
branch
he
"S
tunde + "
T
branch
he
"M
inutes
e + "(back to ale
VC
C
)
St
or
e
-
Clock (La
t
ch)
S
he
ial-
Clock
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)
3 V for DCF77 receiver
X
1
X
2
V
BA
T GND
V
C. C.
SQWSCLSD
A
+
Attention!
Quartz is on the solder side,
to prevent housing
Optional circuit GND can be!
in part, for a light-dependent
Control.
D10D11D12D13GNDAREFGNDA0 D9 A1 A2 A3 A4 A5 GND5V
D8 D7 D6 D5 R 5V 5V GND
X
T
D2 D3 D4 X RST
ATMega 328
The control board (continued)
Above: First, resistors and power supplies
soldered.
Below: The cables to the LEDs and push buttons are
soldered.
Right: The SQWSignalleitung
(Square-
Wave signal) and the
Lines for the
I2C-bus can be soldered
(SCL = Serial Clock
Line, SDA = Serial Data
Line).
S
he
ial-
O
ut (for A
Noden-M
ultiple
x
he)
Sig
signal v
om DCF77 receiver
O
utput
Enable
T
branch
he
"M
ode "
T
branch
he
"S
tunde + "
T
branch
he
"M
inutes
e + "(back to ale
VC
C
)
St
or
e
-
Clock (La
t
ch)
S
he
ial-
Clock
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)
3 V for DCF77 receiver
X
1
X
2
V
BA
T GND
V
C. C.
SQWSCLSD
A
+
Attention!
Quartz is on the solder side,
to prevent housing
Optional circuit GND can be!
in part, for a light-dependent
Control.
D10D11D12D13GNDAREFGNDA0 D9 A1 A2 A3 A4 A5 GND5V
D8 D7 D6 D5 R 5V 5V GND
X
T
D2 D3 D4 X RST
ATMega 328
The control board (continued)
Above: The high components are soldered. In the
LEDs on the correct polarity (? Surface side of the case
to GND)!
Bottom: back to Vcc and GND.
Right: The RBBB is
soldered. Of course
it must be previously
solder together (after
the instructions for
JEE-Labs). With the
Power Jack should be
wait until the power supply
is clarified.
S
he
ial-
O
ut (for A
Noden-M
ultiple
x
he)
Sig
signal v
om DCF77 receiver
O
utput
Enable
T
branch
he
"M
ode "
T
branch
he
"S
tunde + "
T
branch
he
"M
inutes
e + "(back to ale
VC
C
)
St
or
e
-
Clock (La
t
ch)
S
he
ial-
Clock
Silver wire Vcc
(Lötseite!)
Silver wire GND
(Lötseite!)
3 V for DCF77 receiver
X
1
X
2
V
BA
T GND
V
C. C.
SQWSCLSD
A
+
Attention!
Quartz is on the solder side,
to prevent housing
Optional circuit GND can be!
in part, for a light-dependent
Control.
D10D11D12D13GNDAREFGNDA0 D9 A1 A2 A3 A4 A5 GND5V
D8 D7 D6 D5 R 5V 5V GND
X
T
D2 D3 D4 X RST
ATMega 328
A first stage win!
Preparing the frame Ribba
The frame has Ribba
on the back of a
small recess with
which help you to
Remove the rear panel
can.
Hanger
Back
Outer frame
Protective paper
Glass (Note: The edges are natural and therefore the glass is very sharp on the edge!)
Inner frame
Mount
First, we put the wall back onto the glass and then
the inner frame on it. Then we draw the inner edge
of the inner frame on the front and rear
the back wall. This area is "blocking? EXT" on
we can not work later.
Preparing the Ribba frame (continued)
Now we are many things to
The draw back, so
Sharp pencil and go!
First, we write "top" and
"Down" with a permanent
Markers on both sides.
Then we draw an inner frame
with an edge length of
350 mm on both sides (distance
to the outer edge 75 mm).
Then we draw the grid and drill holes on the back of the rear wall. Rather, on any page, this will result to back.
We have 11 columns and 10 rows. A box that has a width of 350 mm / 11 = 31.82 mm and a height of 350 mm / 10 = 35 mm.
These distances can be well in touch with the circle and then pay off at the edge of the inner frame. Be diagonal in the box
drawn. The intersection of the diagonals is the target for the well.
Of course you can also print out the template and thus mark the holes. f Pro-Tip from Michael: Who has not Posterplotter,
the template can be via Adobe Acrobat Reader "tiled" in 1:1 to stick together and print it.
The hole for the markings
Corner LEDs are spaced
25 mm to the rear edge.
Check everything again, if
the holes are drilled first, it is
too late.
Drilling holes
Above: The LEDs are drilled with holes 5 mm in diameter.
Bottom: For taking the silver wire penetrations are
a very fine drill.
Attention! The Ribba frame is not wood, but
from pressed cardboard. Therefore, when drilling with little
Working pressure.
Right: Finished
Drilled back wall
the
QLOCKTWO.
LEDs assemble and solder matrix
The white LEDs
after the
LED soldered to a scheme
Lattice of silver wires
soldered (cathode below
right, anode up
left).
round housing,
long leg =
Anode
? Aches housing,
short leg =
Cathode
Above: The polarity and functionality
an LED can be with an old CR 2032 -
Button cell test. Not with other batteries
(Or only with series resistor).
f Pro-tip: A CR will cost € 0.33 in 2032
Reichelt and 4.50 € in consumer electronics retailing.
Below: First we cut 10
Silver wires and insert them
through the holes, so that we 10
Have transverse rows. The silver wires
should be about 2 inches on the other
Page survive.
Right: Then we equip
the first row at the top with
LEDs. If you like the
whole matrix populated,
impedes the soldering.
Assemble and solder LEDs matrix (continued)
Left: The anode legs
the LEDs are turned down-
(The other
not!) and then the
Silver wire soldered.
The silver wire expands
out during soldering,
Therefore, we collected in the
Mid-to!
Again, a second
Person helps the
Legs pressed down.
Above: The supernatant of the legs is pinched off.
Below: It should look like the first half of the matrix. Because
which is a tedious work, one must at this stage
particular attention to the polarity of the LEDs and clean soldering
. eighth
Right: Then the
Silver wire for the
Cathode feed
and the cathode of the
LEDs are similar to the
Anodes soldered.
Assemble and solder LEDs matrix (continued)
Good job, young Padawan!
i
Matrix isolation
Links: For the isolation
between the anodes and
Cathode, we decompose the
Mats of the
Ribba frame.
Above: We need ten strips in the length of
Frame width.
Below: We divide into 2 cm-long pieces
Strip. The cutting of the strip goes well with a
Carpet knife.
Right: The Strip
are then carefully
series between the anode
(Top) and cathode rows
(Bottom)
pushed. When
while the legs of
Silver wires solve: Super!
We have a cold
Solder joint found that we
would have annoyed afterwards.
Simply resolder.
Matrix test
Left: After the matrix
is isolated, it goes to the
Test. For this we provide
each row and column
once with electricity and
, check whether the corresponding
LED lights up.
Above: For our high-tech turn-matrix LED tester
We do the twist two pieces of silver wire, stick with it
Tesa on an old CR 2032 coin cell and clamp
Alligator clips on.
Below: The LED is mentioned as expected.
CR 2032 button cell
Curved silver wire
Alligator clip
Negative pole
Positive pole
Another stage win!
Connect the control boards
This ribbon cable
Connect the multiplexer
with the LEDMatrix.
Cable to connect Vcc and Ground
Cable to Connect
of serial data, latch,
Clock Output Enable
Shielded cable for
the signal line of the
DCF77 receiver
Button
Cable to Connect
the button
Connect the control boards (continued)
The ribbon cable (or even single cable)
stripped and tinned. Attention! We need one
10 cores and 11 cores again!
Then they are transferred to the outputs from the cathode and
Anode multiplexer soldered.
As mentioned before: Anytime
if somewhere in the cable work
disappear or be solved: Great!
The error would have annoyed us later
(According to experience and there are
enough). Angry but not happy,
and eliminate further you go!
small slot on the side:
Chips fit
Links: If the ribbon cable
are soldered, the chips can
be used. A large
Moment in the life of a
QLOCKTWO-hobbyist!
2 * UDN2981A
4 * 74HC595
1 * DS1307
Right: The chips are (from me
unknown reasons), a small
slightly larger than the holders.
Therefore one must be very carefully
Squeeze your legs a bit.
Below: The chips have as a marker
for the direction of a small recess
or "nose." The versions of these
Nose also.
Below: Now all boards are ready and have "only
still "connected to the matrix and each other
be connected.
Connect the control boards (continued)
Left: The ribbon cable
are best with a
Scalpel, separated into the individual wires.
A few inches can
we can together, as the
Cable under the motherboard
is.
Above: The cables are soldered to the matrix. Attention!
With the marked "1" output is the highest
Series, which means that the cables have the anode
Multiplexers are crossed.
Below: The finished soldered anode multiplexer.
Right: The second multiplexer
is well soldered, the
Wires must not
be crossed. After
the outputs of the matrix
isolated so that there are no shorts
and the cables are located
do not get tangled.
Control boards combine
Left: With red and blue
Cables are the Vcc and
Ground areas on the boards
connected to each other.
Right: Serial Clock, Clock Store
(Latch), serial data and output
Enable are out of the RBBB
brought out. The Serial-Out
Cable must be so long that it
at the anode multiplexer top
watch out! The rest of the cable is
Board to Board by honed.
Bottom: Serial Clock, Clock Store (latch) and output
Enable go right into the cathode multiplexer purely
and left out. The serial data cable goes on the left
it comes from the anode multiplexer.
Right: Serial Clock, Clock Store
(Latch) and output enable
coming from the cathode
Multiplexer. Serial data goes from
RBBB purely Coming up, down
goes out there and is the
Cathode-multiplexer served.
Cathode-M. RBBB
A
Noden-M. Serial Clock, Clock Store
(Latch), output enable
Serial Data
From ug: How does the software on the RBBB?
Links: The development environment invites
one charge under www.arduino.cc
downloads and installs them (together
with the FTDI drivers!).
Right: the extracted arduino folder
Documents must be less than (Windows: "My
Documents ") are located. Otherwise
the libraries are not found.
Below: At the RBBB is connected to the USB-BUB,
this via USB to the computer.
Select Board: Arduino
Duemilanove w / ATmega328
Select a serial port:
something with USB (depending
Different computer).
Qlockthree.pde ö? NEN
Upload to the RBBB
Let there be light!
Good work for a humanoid!
uf Pro-tip: Even without a button you can switch to Vcc.
Corner LEDs connect
Left: The cathode of the corner LEDs
is so bent that they
fits through the small hole.
Above: The LEDs are plugged into the holes.
Below: The anodes of the LEDs are on
the solder matrix. The top left of the first
Series, the top right of the second, lower right
the third and bottom left of the 4th
Right: The cathode is at
the cathode-multiplexer
soldered. (Ordering: Top
left, top right, bottom right,
bottom left.)
round housing,
long leg =
Anode
? Aches housing,
short leg =
Cathode
DCF77-receiver connect
Above: the DCF77 receiver from Pollin is one
incorrect data in. Is a recent order
second sheet outside of antistatic packaging
at - then that's true, but still difficult
to interpret.
Shown above: the left is the yellow power supply (the
lowered in the new sheet to 3 volts). The
second pin from the right is the signal line. The receiver
reacts recommend? RURAL to disturbances of all kinds, especially
by the high-frequency multiplexing. It is therefore
He mounted far away in space (top right) and the
Shielded signal cable. Instead of a shielded
Cable you can take a normal cable and
Wrap in aluminum foil, which is then set to ground.
The two remaining pins go to ground, one on
Power supply and the other is "PON", which is
the recipient can put to sleep (which we do not
) use.
Above: the DCF77 receiver is connected to the control board
connected.
f Pro-Tip: The quality of the received signal can
viewing of the LED. Since the time signal with a
Pulse length of 100ms (for 0) and length of 200ms
Is (for 1) transmitted per second, the LED must
in sync with the LED from the Real-Time Clock
light up. Once per minute for a second, they must
remain dark, this is the synchronization point.
If the LED is plowed wild? The reception is disturbed
(Through the computer monitor or the like).
With the electronics we are now (almost) done! Even the buttons are missing, but the
Let us lift till the end. Since the yes button with the housing and the
Control board are connected, is the east? NEN / closing the frame Ribba
then more difficult. So we just make everything else ready, and finally
then come the buttons. Va bene?
Light grid build
Light grid build (continued)
11 * horizontal (cut twice)
12 * vertical (cut twice)
The light curtain is designed to prevent the LEDs on adjacent characters.
For this purpose we cut out the cardstock strips 2.5 cm high with a length
of 35 cm. These strips, we divide into 11 parts (on 11 strips) and in 10 parts
(On 12 strips). Along these subdivisions, we cut the strips to
Half twice. Then we put the strips together and get sent
the grid shown below.
This is one of the fiddly work around, so stay calm!
350 mm
25 mm
31.8 mm
35 mm
Cut at these markers twice!
Light grid build (continued)
Left and right: The half
cut lattice strips
be plugged together.
f Pro-Tip: If you have the opportunity
has the lattice strips
Laminating: use absolutely!
They are thus much
stable and not break
quickly.
Below: It looks like a grid, if you only cut the
executes once! Spans the entire lattice, since the paper
Although thin, but still some space in the average
needs.
Below: So it looks better. By the double-cut
have the strips and place the grid is pretty regularly.
As a reward, it can sometimes donned
(Next page).
Light grid build (continued)
e
This is so cool!
Light grid build (continued)
Links: Now we need the
"External walls" are mounted.
We need a couple of 2.5 cm
large piece of paper and Klebsto?
(And patience).
Right: From the paper strips
we make a bunch of 2.5
cm high "corners" with which we
then the strips for the outer walls
at the free-standing lattice strips
. stick
For the corner LEDs, we need four separate boxes.
The pattern is right on a scale of 1:1. Just
, cut, fold on the dotted lines
and stick together.
Light grid build (continued)
w
I feel the power ...
Foil laminate
triggered slide
Glass plate
Kitchen towels
Water
Washing-up liquid
Glass cleaner Paper towel
Squeegee
Kitchen sponge
(New)
Gloves
Foil laminate (continued)
First, the glass plate with
the glass cleaner cleaned clean.
Between the film and what later
Glass is, can never be removed
be.
Then the glass plate with
Eingeschmoddert dishwater.
Tip: Simplest detergent without
Additives such as hand balm, etc.
. take
With the removal of the film of
the carrier material be careful, it
remain like the delicate internal components
depend on letters.
At best, pull the carrier film
over a table edge after
downwardly away. A second person is
helpful here!
Foil laminate (continued)
Left: The drawn film.
Right: The film is with the
Detergent eingeschmodderte
Glass down. By the detergent
stick it been fixed yet, but
can be positioned. Who (like me)
much detergent is used,
may need only once on the
Front a little detergent
. Squeeze
Below: At the back we now press on the middle
Starting with the blade between the soap film
and glass out.
Below: The finished front panel with the laminated
Film is to sample on the light grid. That looks
already pretty good, right?
Final: mount pushbutton
Drilling into the frame Ribba
we have three holes. The buttons
should not all three side by side
lie, because you then
later, no longer knows
which switches the importance
has. It is better to
Mode button on one and
the control switch to the other
To create page.
flush
Above: The tiny scrap of a button are too short
We must therefore about the borehole, the frame thickness
make a little thinner. The frame is made of pressed cardboard,
Thus goes the whole with a carpet knife
well.
Below: The framework should be diluted so that the
Button is flush with the frame. Do not worry,
you can then press him still.
Right: Caution! The buttons
have a narrow and a
wide side! Turn
between the short side, the
sides form a broad
Short circuit.
Final: mount switches (continued)
Left: Two legs off we tweak
soldered to the other two legs
we have a red cable (that comes later
to Vcc) and a colorful cord.
Right: The soldered legs
We turn around to the button. The
Button is between the later
Inner frame (spacer) and
the outer wall, so he should be so
occupy little space as possible.
Right: To the button with hot glue
pour the frame
firmly clamped, the probe can
you are good with xieren thumbtacks?.
Matted Prints of residues serve as
thin spacers so that the
Button is not pushed out from below
be.
Below: Our three keys, each with a red cord for
Vcc and colorful cables for connection to the RBBB.
Final: mount switches (continued)
O
utput
Enable
T
branch
he
"M
ode "
T
branch
he
"S
tunde + "
T
branch
he
"M
inutes
e + "(back to ale
VC
C
)
X
1
X
2
V
BA
T GND
V
C. C.
SQWSCLSD
A
+
D10D11D12D13GNDAREFGNDA0 D9 A1 A2 A3 A4 A5 GND5V
D8 D7 D6 D5 R 5V 5V GND
X
T
D2 D3 D4 X RST
ATMega 328
Links: The buttons are now
with lots of hot glue
"Cast". You need
then for a while
Cool, so be patient.
Right: For the "final assembly"
we put in the back wall
frame without the front plate,
as they are later
is. It is with books
highlighted, so they are a little
is pushed upward.
three of the buttons "back to Vcc"
the three colored wires from the probes
Links: Now we solder
the cable of the probe
to the control board.
Red wire go
somewhere to Vcc, the
colorful to the RBBB.
Final: fix light grid and feet cut
Left: The light grid with
Hot glue dots. Once
around it.
Receiver
Right: The corners are just as
taped. It can also
equal to the DCF77 receiver and
its antenna sticking. The
Antenna should be held in parallel to
Frame may be aligned.
Right: cut the cork
We in three slices, the three
Slices in each of four "pieces of cake."
Bottom: As spacers we prepare for the boards
small feet in front of cork. At best this is the
Cork from a suitable Barolos of Langhe.
Final: PCBs stick
Left: Four are from the legs
glued to the back wall.
Above: The board is glued to the Korkbeine.
Bottom: Similar to the anode of the multiplexer is also
Cathode-multiplexer bonded.
Right: The control board is
glued on. Attention! The
highest part of the board (the
Power Jack) may not at the top
maximum of 2.5 cm from the
Base plate must be removed.
max. 2.5 cm
Final: Panel Insert
i
You have learned much, young padawan!
CONGRATULATIONS!
Appendix A - How does the QLOCKTWO?
LED Matrix multiplexing: the shift register
The matrix consists of QLOCKTWO (besides the four corner LEDs) from a grid of LEDs with 10 rows and 11 columns. That's a total of 114 LEDs. It
there is no microcontroller with 114 outputs for each LED can be controlled individually to. The ATmega328-used by us
Microcontroller from Atmel for example, has 14 digital and 6 analog inputs and outputs. To increase the number of outputs, one uses frequently? G and
like the 74HC595 shift register.
With a shift register is a building block in the data (bits) are pushed through a line (shifted), and this
Then provides data to many outputs. Thus, we suddenly have 8 outputs more!
74HC595
11101010
1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0
+5 V
Time
1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0
q
But how does the shift register,
When a bit is over? Is the power
with him?
These data bits are called
TTL level, does that mean, a binary
0 corresponds to 0 volts (or
"Low"), one corresponding to binary 1 +5
Volts (or "high").
No, the power is not with him, but in addition to
the data line (Serial Data) there is a
Line, which sets the clock (serial clock). Always
on this line if the level from low to high
jumps, is a bit too late.
5V
Time
1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0
5V
Time
Serial Data
Serial Clock
pure-shifter
LED Matrix multiplexing: the shift register (continued)
a
All well and good, and where white
the shift register then when we with the data
are finished?
h
Yeah but see Bings
four shift registers in the master plan?
In addition to the data line (Serial Data) and the
Clock line (serial clock), there is a stop
(Latch or store-clock). Whenever these transom
Line is low, data may be written. Is
they are high, the output data to the outputs.
5V
Time
1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0
5V
Time
Serial Data
Serial Clock
5V
Time
Store-clock (Latch)
74HC595
... 10100110110110110101101
1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0
74HC595
1 1 0 1 0 0 1 1
74HC595
0 1 1 0 1 1 0 1
74HC595
1 0 1 0 1 1 0 1
We need more than 8 outputs. Fortunately enough, however,
a data line. Each shift register has a "spillover".
One moves into more data than a shift-register
can absorb, the excess data from
pushed out the overflow. These can then
shove the next shift register.
Overflow
LED Matrix multiplexing: the shift register (continued)
VCC = Power Plus (Common Collector Voltage)
The first QA = Output
The SER = serial data
OE = Output enabled (Output Enable)
RCLK = store-clock (Latch)
SRCLK = Serial Clock
Serial SRCLR = Clear
QH '= The overflow
The second Output = QB
The third Output = QC
The fourth Output = QD
The 5th Output = QE
The 6th Output = QF
The 7th Output = QG
The 8th Output = QH
Power supply negative (ground) GND =
Just as the bottom of the shift register is shown in the datasheet. Those who were paying attention very closely to discover two pins, the
not been described so far are.
OE = Output Enable (Output ON) is a pin, which can be used all the outputs on and off. The line above means the OE
OE is an inverted pin. This in turn means OE is active when the level is to low.
Serial SRCLR = Clear (erase data) is a pin that allows to delete all contents of the register. SRCLR is also an inverted pin.
b
Toll: Three statements
and we have just LEDs for 114
4 * 8 = 32 outputs!
That's right, and therefore we use
one trick is not getting any LED
their own output, but a
get a whole row of LEDs
The output. And a column too! (Right
schematically an example with 3 times 3
LEDs.)
LED Matrix multiplexing: the matrix
For simplicity we consider hereafter only a 8x8 matrix, but the principle applies to our (theoretically up to) 16x16 matrix.
74HC595
1 1 0 1 1 1 1 1
74HC595
0
0
1
0
0
0
0
0
We can now turn on an LED on by
the side with the positive poles of the LEDs (anodes) a
One issue and on the side with the negative poles
(Cathode) a 0 Since an LED is a diode and the
Current only in one direction through leaves remain, all
other LEDs are dark, though tension is applied.
74HC595
1 1 0 1 1 0 1 1
74HC595
0
0
1
1
0
0
0
0
The problem is, we switch more than one
Row and column is a light, repeating every Betro? Enes
LEDs! So we could never just above the LED
right and bottom left panels let!
. Cool! But an LED
is a little bit, right? . I always knew that
The rebels are too stupid to!
LED Matrix multiplexing: the matrix (continued)
p
This is so cool!
And in the QLOCKTWO
the 3736 seconds per
done!
We nevertheless can output patterns, we're going to keep only one column! Only the first, then the second and so on. And
do we so quickly that it looks like the human eye as a stationary image. So powerful that a tube TV for that matter. This
E? Ect called "image persistence" or "persistence of vision".
74HC595
0 1 1 1 1 1 1 1
74HC595
0
1
1
1
0
0
0
0
First Column
74HC595
1 0 1 1 1 1 1 1
74HC595
1
1
0
0
0
0
0
0
Second Column
74HC595
1 1 0 1 1 1 1 1
74HC595
1
1
0
0
0
0
0
0
Third Column
And so w
ince
and so he w
ince
it up to 8t
s gap
e
...
Representation of the words
The words that are necessary for the representation of time, are now simply as a bit-pattern de ned? Who then spend it on the shift register
can. These de nitions are? In the source code for the de? Nition of the stored numbers.
# Define FIVE matrix [0] | = 0b0000000111100000
# Define TEN matrix [1] | = 0b1111000000000000
# Define QUARTER matrix [2] | = 0b0000111111100000
# Define TWENTY matrix [1] | = 0b0000111111100000
# Define HALF-matrix [4] | = 0b1111000000000000
# Define THREE QUARTERS matrix [2] | = 0b1111111111100000
Which line?
Which LEDs in the row?
b
So much so that one can
but understand what should be a 0-th row?
And what is the "|" character?
In programming, it counts as opposed to normal life from zero. Has
to 16 lines, counting from 0 to 15 Then there are also 16 so-called "states".
The "|" character is a binary "or". It ultimately causes that a line does not match the
Word is overwritten, but only overlaid. In the bottom line in the example above
are the words "HALF" and "FIVE". If it's half past five, would the "FIVE" the word
"HALF" to overwrite. By superimposing the two words together shine.
{
These five bits are left
(16 bits, we could drive, but in the QLOCKTWO we only need 11)
The software (simplified)
void loop () {
getDateDs1307 ();
setWords (hour minute);
setMinutes (minute);
if (digital read (minutePlusPin) == HIGH) {
minute + +;
}
if (digital read (hourePlusPin) == HIGH) {
hour + +;
}
if (digital read (modePin) == HIGH) {
mode + +;
}
if (mode! = BLANK) {
write matrix ();
}
digitalWrite (dcf77Led, digital read (dcf77Signal));
digitalWrite (rtcSQWLed, digital read (rtcSQWSignal));
const char * v = dcf77.getDateTime ();
second = 0;
dcf77.getMinutes minute = ();
dcf77.getHoures hour = ();
setDateDs1307 ();
}
The loop () loop is executed indefinitely.
Here we read from the RTC.
The hours to write the matrix.
The minutes to write the matrix.
If you pull the trigger for the minutes?
If you pull the trigger for hours?
If you pull the trigger for the mode?
Matrix output, if not eliminated.
Status LED DCF77 signal.
Status LED Real-time clock.
DCF77 receiver read.
Time from DCF77 receiver take over.
Appendix B - Outlooks
q
And what happens now?
Has it been all this?
This is a super? Ux LED. It's small? Oh
and in addition to an enormous brightness
a viewing angle of 120 °. It is
more difficult to process, but one
could one? Acheres and therefore more elegant
Build housing.
This is an RGB pixel of bliptronics. He
can emit light in 32,768 colors! And
this with a beam angle of 160 °!
Imagine: the matrix, the
Color change, or between words
fade!
120 °
10 mm in height!
40 °
470 mm height!
(Theoretical)
3 mm in height!
160 °
Our LEDs
